Finding Aid for W. L. Williams Papers, 1962-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
W. L. Williams Papers 1962-1986, 1967-1986
Williams, W. L. (William Lee), 1937-1986
2 linear feet
9533 Aa 2
University of Michigan physicist whose work concentrated in atomic physics, notably hydrogen parity experiments; also participated in astrophysics research with Arthur Rich, dean for research at the University of Michigan College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1985-1986. Grant proposal materials, correspondence, notes from experiments and research, course materials, papers pertaining to Williams' research at the University of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Shelly F. Williams (donor 8318 ) in January 1995.
The collection is open to research.
William L. Williams was born on May 28, 1937 in Chickasha, Oklahoma. He received his B.S. in physics from Rice University in 1959 and his M.S. from Dartmouth in 1961, with his master's thesis research resulting in a Physics Review article and, in collaboration with W.T. Doyle, a Physics Review Letters article.
Williams received his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1965, working with his thesis director Vernon Hughes. Their 'Experimental Test for Mass Anisotropy Based on Magnetic Resonance' essay won first prize in the Gravity Research Foundation Competition in 1969.
Williams came to the University of Michigan as an instructor with the Department of Physics in 1965. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1966, associate professor in 1969, and professor in 1976. The bulk of Williams' research focused on atomic physics, notably work with hydrogen as exemplified by his hydrogen parity experiment.
For the first half of the 1970s, Williams was also involved in astrophysics research. This included work at the Cerro-Tololo International Observatory in Chile where he and Arthur Rich researched the electromagnetic properties of white dwarfs.
Williams' final project was his work on the Muon g-2 experiment at Yale University. Williams was again working with Vernon Hughes, and a sizeable group representing the national and international physics community, to establish a new measurement of the magnetic moment of the muon. The project was funded after Williams' death.
Williams was also involved in academic affairs at the University of Michigan. He served on the Department of Physics Executive Committee and as Associate Chairman. In 1985 he was named associate dean for research in the college of Literature, Science and the Arts (LSA).
Williams died in a plane crash, November 11, 1986.
The papers of William L. Williams are contained in four series: Biographical Information, Research Interests, Course Materials, and a Topical File.
Subjects:
Williams, W. L. (William Lee), 1937-; Physicists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physics--Experiments.; Physics--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.
- Biographical 1986-1988
  Biographical Information (1986-1988; 1 folder) includes an early 1980s curriculum vitae for Williams as well as memorial pieces authored by former colleagues, notably an invited paper presented by Arthur Rich at the Baltimore meeting of the American Physical Society.
  - Biographical Information 1986-1988 (Box 1)
- Research Interests 1967-1986
  Research Interests (1967-1986; 0.7 linear ft.) documents Williams' areas of interests and concerns in physics. The series covers the years of Williams' research career and contains documentation of the Muon g-2 experiment group which proposed a new measurement of the magnetic moment of the muon, a project he worked on up until his death. This series contains a Grant Materials subseries that documents Williams' involvement with various projects that solicited grants from funding agencies, most often the National Science Foundation (NSF). This series documents the grant application and maintenance process and contains letters of inquiry, referees' reports of proposals, budget plans, letters approving funding and letters denying funding. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Astro-Statistical Analysis undated (Box 1)
  - EDM 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Elastic Scattering of a-Particles From Be9 1960s (Box 1)
  - Four-Level Problem 1979 (Box 1)
  - Grant Materials 1975-1986
    - NBS Precision Measurements Grant circa 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation (NSF) 1975-1986, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Helucholt's Coil 1965-1979 (Box 1)
  - H-Parity Experiment circa 1984 (Box 1)
  - H-PNC, Polarized E-N Scatter 1979 (Box 1)
  - H PNC, Robiscoe 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - H-PNC, Seattle circa 1982 (Box 1)
  - Kulak, notes on 1970 (Box 1)
  - Levy Lineshape Analysis 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Local Lorentz Invariance circa 1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mass Anisotropy circa 1967 (Box 1)
  - M*B Experiments, summary on (Williams?) undated (Box 1)
  - Metastable Helium-Low Energy Electron Scattering Cross Section. Referee's Report 1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Two-Cavity Experiment 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Muon g-2 Experiment 1984-1985, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Muon g-2 Experiment (Blueprints) 1986 (Box 1)
  - Neutral Hydrogen Detector, post 1971 (Box 1)
  - Parity Non-Conservation in the H-Atom 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Polarization 1971 (Box 1)
  - Rydberg States in H+ and Cs circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - Slow H (2s) Beam 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - THEM Formula 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Three-Level Problem 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - T-Invariance Paper 1986 (Box 1)
  - Two Level Problem, Density Matrix 1980 (Box 1)
  - Two-Quantum Transitional (?) 1979 (Box 1)
  - Unpublished Manuscript circa 1983 (Box 1)
- Course Materials 1962-1984
  Course Materials (1962-1984; .8 linear ft.) is divided into two subseries. The Yale University subseries contains course materials and notebooks accumulated during Williams' years as a Ph.D. student there. The University of Michigan subseries contains course notes, exams, and problem sets and solutions for courses Williams taught over a span of 19 years. Contained is material created for Physics 405, 453, 512 and 644. These materials provide insight into Williams' teaching methods and how they changed over the years.
  - Yale University (courses attended, etc.)
    - Physics 150b (Relativity) Course Notes 1962 (Box 2)
    - Notebooks 1963-1964, 4 volumes
      - Mass Anisotropy. He3 Magnetic Moment I 1963 (Box 2)
      - Mass Anisotropy. He3 Magnetic Moment II 1964 (Box 2)
      - He3 Magnetic Moment III 1964 (Box 2)
      - Notebook I undated (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Physics 405 (Intermediate Electricity and Magnetism) 1983
      - Solutions 1983 (Box 2)
      - Exams and Course Notes 1983 (Box 2)
    - Physics 453 (Atomic Physics) 1966-1984
      - Course Notes undated (Box 2)
      - Course Notes, Exams, and Homework 1966-1981, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Exams and Course Notes 1977 (Box 2)
      - Exams and Problem Solutions 1977 (Box 2)
      - Course Notes 1978 (Box 2)
      - Exams and Problem Sets 1984 (Box 2)
    - Physics 512 (Quantum Theory-Atomic Structures)
      - Problem Sets 1977 (Box 2)
    - Physics 644 (Advanced Atomic Physics) 1976
      - Course Notes 1976 (Box 2)
- Topical File 1968-1983
  Topical File (1968-1983; .2 linear ft.) documents Williams' involvement in areas outside of the realm of academic physics. This series is divided into two subseries. The Conferences, Talks, etc. subseries provides information about talks given by Williams and documents his involvement in the international physics community. The Miscellaneous subseries documents Williams' interest in non- physics topics and those making applied use of physics research.
  - Conferences, Talks, etc.
    - Mach's Principle Undergraduate Talk undated (Box 2)
    - International Symposium on the "Physics of one-and two-electron atoms," Munich 1968 (Box 2)
    - Yale University Flint Lectures 1978 (Box 2)
    - Workshop on Weak Interactions and Neutrons, Javea, Spain 1982 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Arms Control 1983 (Box 2)
    - Dental Imaging Corporate Venture 1982 (Box 2)
    - Military/Classified Research 1982 (Box 2)